Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף Daf is קכ"ו, Kuf Chaf
Vav, בבא בתרא Bava Batra 126. We pick up at the very
top of
קכ"ו, Kuf Chaf Vav, אמר רב הונא, Amar Rav Huna, very top
line, אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, and we're continuing to the
discussion about the בכור Bechor getting the double portion, but that it's
only במוחזק, Be-Muchzak, only something the father already is in possession of,
not בראוי, Be-Ra'uy, not something that was coming his way but he
did not take possession of. There's a debate exactly how broadly or
narrowly to assume those parameters, but we assume them pretty narrowly that
he really has to be in possession. And there was even a
debate about a loan,
but even money that he had lent out that was coming back
to him, and even there though we consider that to be ראוי
Ra'uy and not מוחזק. Muchzak. Okay, and now we continue in a
related topic. אמר רב הונא אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Huna Amar
Rav Assi, בכור שמיחה מיחה. Bechor she-micha micha. If a בכור Bechor
objects, that is a good objection. Now, what exactly is the context
is not clear. I'm going to read this the way the רשב"ם
Rashbam reads it, which is that if the בכור Bechor says, okay,
but I don't want, let's say they inherit fields, and there are,
I don't know, three brothers, and so we divide it and four
fields. So the בכור Bechor gets, is going to get two of
the fields. And then the בכור Bechor says,
I want to take my two fields, and they haven't divided it
yet,
I want to take my double portion, and I don't want you
to do any work on it because since the work you're going
to do and then if it improves it's going to be considered
ראוי, Ra'uy,
then I don't want that split equally. I want to do the
work on the fields, I want to get my portion, do the
work, and then it'll be my fields that improve, and I don't
want it to be that you work all of the fields and
it gets divided equally. So he protests. He says, don't do work
on the fields, I want us to divide it, I want to
get my extra portion, I want to work on it, so that
the improvement will also of my extra portion will also come to
me. So he says that's good, that is a good protesting, and
if they then go ahead and work on it, they're actually improving
something that is already his and it's not considered that he's getting
a double portion in ראוי, Ra'uy, it's considered that the portion that
already deserves to come to him is being, has to some degree
come to him and is now being improved. Okay, so that would
be the way that he would get entitled then to the improved
value of it.
Now, let's see so how the גמרא Gemara deals with that. אמר
רבה מסתבר טעמיה דרב אסי בענבים ובצרום זיתים ומסקום. Amar Rabba mistavar
ta'ama de-Rav Assi ba-anavim u-vatzrum zeitim u-maskum.
I'm not going to 100% say that that's a true across the
board because at the end of the day, even if he's protesting
and says don't work on it, they haven't actually divided up the
fields. He doesn't know which field is his and which field isn't
his yet. So even if he's going to get two, which two?
And if they go ahead and work on it, they're not, it's
not that his portion has improved, it still belongs to the generic
estate even though he said he didn't want them to work on
it. And if it still belongs to the generic estate and now
the whole estate improves, that's considered ראוי. Ra'uy. So he says, I
will only accept this ruling if it is something that is not
a substantial difference. If basically you went ahead and you harvested the
grapes or you harvested the olives. The word בצירה מסיקה Batzira maskika
is just different words for harvesting between grapes and olives, excuse me,
I said oil, olives.
In that type of a case, remember even cases even the rabbis
say that a שבח דממילא, Shevach di-mimmela, where it's basically the object
hasn't really transformed in a significant way, is considered to be מוחזק.
Muchzak. So that case I'll concede.
But then the question is why did he even really need to
protest and to object if it's considered to be a type of
a שבח דממילא? Shevach di-mimmela? All right, but somehow his protesting means
that as long as now he told them not to do it,
they did it anyway, it's substantially the same but just worth a
little bit more, that is, that will be considered his, not ראוי.
Ra'uy. דרכום לא, Darchum lo, but if they actually went ahead and
they pressed the grapes, turned it into grape juice, or unfermented wine,
pressed the olives, turned it into oil, that's a major transformation. And
as long as the fields have not been divided, even if he
protests, he still doesn't yet have his specific portion, and that's considered
ראוי, Ra'uy, and he's not entitled to it. ורב יוסף אמר אפילו
דרכום. Ve-Rav Yosef amar afilu darchum. Even if you go ahead and
press them. So based on the way that I've framed it, which
is the רשב"ם's Rashbam way, we might be inclined to say that
רב יוסף Rav Yosef says even if we can't identify which fields,
the fact that he's protested means that it's like his extra portion
has already come to him and now it's his portion that's improved,
it's not the estate that's improved. But the גמרא Gemara refuses to
go down that road and the גמרא Gemara says like this. If
they press the olives and the grapes, מעיקרא ענבי והשתא חמרא, meikara
invi vehashta chamra, originally it was just grapes, and now it's wine.
So it's a major transformation. So the גמרא Gemara says even without
his protesting, as long as you haven't actually divided the estate, it's
still the estate. He still doesn't yet have his portion. And therefore,
any improvement that is substantial is considered to be ראוי, ra'uy, something
new, and he's not entitled to a double portion. So how does
any, how does this make sense? It's still ראוי. ra'uy. So the
גמרא Gemara says כדאמר רב עוקבא בר חמא ליתן לו דמי היזק
ענביו. ked'amar Rav Ukva bar Chama leiten lo d'mei hezek anavav. Like
רב עוקבא בר חמא Rav Ukva bar Chama says, we're not talking
that he actually gets a double portion in the improved value from
grapes to wine, but in case somehow something went wrong and they
destroyed the grapes in the process or they were damaged and now
it's worthless,
he is entitled now to the damage that was done to it.
הכי נמי יהיב לו דמי היזק ענביו. hachi nami yahiv lo d'mei
hezek anavav. Here too he gets the damage. So not at all
like we sounded like that once he says don't do, don't work
on it, I want us to divide it, I want to work
on it, that will then entitle him to any improvement, a double
portion. Nope, the גמרא Gemara insists that even after מיחה, mecha, it
still is the estate, it's not his portion.
So the one that says but he gets if they pressed it,
what does that mean? That means that he doesn't lose from his
double portion if damage occurs, because he has said that he did
not want them to work it. What does that mean? Let's say
all of the grapes are worth, again the case of three brothers,
all of the grapes are worth four hundred dollars. So he's going
to get two hundred dollars worth of grapes, and the other two
brothers will divide the other two hundred between them. And he says
don't work the grapes, I want to work them myself. The other
brothers don't go ahead and listen to him. They work the grapes,
they press the wine, and now they actually didn't know what they
were doing, and now the whole thing is worth just two hundred
dollars, not four hundred dollars. So rather than saying, well, now we'll
divide that two hundred dollars into four portions, he gets one hundred,
they get fifty each, we'll say, no, he protested. He says don't
work it. So he's entitled to the original two hundred dollars of
the grapes that would have come his way anyway because he said
I don't want you to work that portion of the estate.
That seems like it has very little to do with the idea
of בכור, bechor, it just seems like if somebody protests his other
brothers working the estate before it's been divided, then he doesn't have
to suffer any losses that are incurred. But that is how we
are interpreting it. Okay. And the way the רשב"ם Rashbam then says
it, it almost becomes a type of like a גזל, gezel, that
then they're stealing his grapes by using it against his agreement. And
since they're stealing it, then they have to pay him as a
כגזלן. kegazlan. Of course, again, that's a little complicated because he doesn't
really own any specific grapes yet if he,
as we said, the גמרא Gemara is still conceptualizing this as all
part of the estate, not divided yet. But because he's protesting, he
is not going to suffer if their going ahead and doing it
causes damage. Okay. היכא איתמר דרב עוקבא בר חמא? heicha itmar d'Rav
Ukva bar Chama? Where is רב עוקבא בר חמא Rav Ukva bar
Chama said? אהא דאמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל בכור פשוט שהניח להן
אביהן ענבים ובצרום זיתים ומסקום. aha d'amar Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel bechor
pashut she'heniach lahen avihen anavim uvatzarum zeitim umasakum. So similar type of
a case. The father left them grapes, and they went ahead and
harvested them, or olives, and they went ahead and also harvested them.
בכור נוטל פי שנים, bechor notel pi shnayim, the בכור bechor gets
double, אפילו דרכום, afilu darchum, even if they've been pressed. So again,
these two rulings, the simple sense of both this ruling here of
רב יהודה אמר שמואל Rav Yehuda amar Shmuel and the ruling
of רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, seem very much to feel that at
that certain stage it is his grapes, even if it hasn't been
divided yet, and it's not a problem of ראוי, ra'uy, and he
does get the benefit and the פי שנים. pi shnayim. But again,
the גמרא Gemara just really rejects this conclusion. And the גמרא Gemara
says דרכום מעיקרא ענבי והשתא חמרא. darchum meikara invi vehashta chamra.
How can you say pressing if we're going to interpret
מוחזק muchzak as very narrow, then all of this is ראוי ra'uy
and presumably even after protesting, as long as it hasn't been divided,
he should not be entitled to the change, the benefit that comes
from grapes turning into wine. That's ראוי. ra'uy. So אמר רב עוקבא
בר חמא ליתן לו דמי היזק ענביו. amar Rav Ukva bar Chama
leiten lo d'mei hezek anavav. No, what we're talking about is that
they damaged his portion. And because they damaged his portion and it
was done against his, or they damaged everything, but that means that
he's suffering as well. And because it was done against his protests,
he should not have to suffer losses that were incurred because of
what the other brothers did when he clearly objected to them going
ahead and doing it. All right. So it's a really not a
very satisfying גמרא. Gemara. First of all, it's unclear if that's even
what the whole גמרא Gemara means. It's a very vague גמרא. Gemara.
What do we mean היזק? Hezek? What's the scenario of היזק? Hezek?
What do we mean מיחא? Micha? But anyway, but within that reading
of the רשב"ם, Rashbam, it's very, it's really, you know, certainly unsatisfying,
and it is interesting to wonder at what stage is the בכור
bechor entitled to say I want to be get my portion now
so I can start improving it, and then it stops being considered
part of the estate. But the way the רשב"ם Rashbam reads it,
that won't happen until an actual formal חלוקה chalukah has been done.
All right, let's continue. אמר רב אסי, Amar Rav Assi, בכור שנטל
חלק כפשוט, bechor she'natal chelek k'pashut, ויטר. viter. If a בכור bechor
gets a portion like a normal son, he has ויטר, viter, he
has like waived his rights. So what does that mean?
So let's take a look. So the גמרא Gemara says,
מאי ויטר? mai viter? What does it mean that he has waived
his rights? רב פפא משמיה דרבא אמר, ויטר באותה שדה. Rav Papa
mishmeih d'Rava amar viter b'ota sadeh. He has waived his rights in
that field. So we said before that, you know, this
idea בכור, bechor, יתן לו, yitein lo, give him, that the חלק
בכורה chelek bechorah is to some level considered like a מתנה. matanah.
And opposed to a actual inheritance where you can give away property
you inherit, but you cannot refuse to inherit it, that happens automatically,
the idea of the חלק בכורה chelek bechorah is considered like an
extra gift and you can refuse it. Although it's
not made exactly clear what is that timeframe in which you can
say that you've refused it, when can you say it, when can
you reverse it, etc. But here the גמרא Gemara is working within
that understanding that it can be refused. So it says let's say
they're coming to divide up the stuff, and they say okay, so
now we've got these portions here, you know, we've got this field,
we've got three brothers, and the בכור bechor says it's fine, I'll
just take a third. Okay, he's נוטל חלק כפשוט, notel chelek k'pashut,
he does not demand his חלק בכורה. chelek bechorah. So that becomes
as a waiving of his right to his בכור bechor portion. So
now we're going to have to see how much. So let's take
a look. So where were we? מאי ויטר? mai viter? רב פפא
משמיה דרבא אמר ויטר באותה שדה. Rav Papa mishmeih d'Rava amar viter
b'ota sadeh,
In that very field, you've waived your portion because you've agreed to
take a third. So that seems almost obvious. Maybe it's telling us
you haven't waived it elsewhere. Or maybe it means that now you
can't come back and say you know what, I changed my mind,
I actually am entitled to a בכור bechor portion. Once you waive
your right, you waive your right. Okay, that's that idea about מתנה
קריה רחמנא. matanah karya Rachmana. באותה
שדה,
B'ota
sadeh, רב פפי משמיה דרבא אמר Rav Pappi mishmeih d'Rava amar no,
ויטר בכל הנכסים כולם. viter b'chol hanechasim kulam. Once you agree to
take to waive your בכור bechor right in the field, it's read
as an implicit waiving of your entire double portion. So if we've
got liquid assets, and we've got cars, and we've got real estate,
and all that stuff, once in one of those divisions, and it's
understood that we're not just going to liquefy it all and translate
it all into dollars, we're going to divide each genre of property,
and once in one of those divisions you do not insist on
your חלק בכורה, chelek bechorah, it's considered that you've waived it completely.
So let's take a look. רב פפא משמיה דרבא אמר Rav Papa
mishmeih d'Rava amar, ויטר באותה שדה, viter b'ota sadeh. קסבר אין לו
לבכור קודם חלוקה. kasavar ein lo l'bechor kodem chalukah.
Okay, he says the reason
I'm not going to consider it that you know I'm going to
consider it that you only waived in that field and not for
everything is because until it's been divided, you don't actually yet have
the portion.
So you don't have the portion in order to waive it. When
they're dividing the fields, that is the moment when it is being
decided what is your בכור bechor portion, and that's the moment when
you are in a position to waive and to say I don't
want to take my בכור bechor portion. But you can't waive something
that hasn't happened yet. You can't say but I
waive my בכור bechor portion when it comes to the stocks, when
it comes to the money in the bank. I mean you could
say it, but it's not yet binding and you don't yet have
it in order to waive it, and we're not in the process
that your waiving makes any difference. When we then come to divide
it, then you can retract what you said before, then you can
basically say you know what, I changed my mind, I do actually
want my בכור bechor portion in the stocks or in the cash,
okay? So since it's not yet the time and you don't yet
have any rights to it, you're going to get it later, you're
not going to get it now, saying you waive it now doesn't
mean anything. It only means something on the thing that is being
divided right now. רב פפי, Rav Pappi, skipping the parentheses, משמיה דרבא
אמר ויטר בכל הנכסים כולם, mishmeih d'Rava amar viter b'chol hanechasim kulam,
קסבר יש לו לבכור קודם חלוקה, kasavar yesh lo l'bechor kodem chalukah,
ומדאחלי בהאי אחלי בכולהו. mide'achali be'hai achali b'chulhu. No, you do have,
meaning you don't know which yet portion is yours, but even though
it's a gift, you do have rights. So we have this whole
estate, you know. So again in the case of four brothers you're
entitled to 50 percent of the estate. 25 percent as a פשוט,
pashut, 25 percent as a בכור. bechor. You right now have a
50 percent right, a 50 percent claim in the estate. So therefore,
if you if we believe, now we have to assume that expressing
your waiving your בכור bechor in one genre is understood to be
a waiving of it across the board. But if we're prepared to
assume that, then it will have the effect of you have now
forfeited your right to that 25 percent claim you have as a
בכור. bechor. Okay, so there's two things you have to get to
to say ויתר בכל נכסים כולן. vita bechol nechasim kulan. Number one
is to read when I say I waive my בכור bechor rights
in the fields to be understood as saying I'm waiving my בכור
bechor rights across the board. It's not clear to me why we
should assume that. Okay, but anyway, that is assumption number one. Even
if you assume that,
it will only be binding if you actually also assume that I
right now have a claim to a my בכור bechor portion in
the whole estate. And then I can waive it and then it's
and then I've lost it. But if I don't have it until
I get it, which is what the first position רב פפא Rav
Papa said, then my waiving doesn't mean anything. Okay, so it's a
nice conceptual issue. If it's a מתנה matana that you are in
a position to waive, so רב פפא Rav Papa says, well a
gift is not the same as a right. And a gift is
something you get when it's being given. So you can only waive
it when it's being given. And if you waived in the field,
it's not yet the time to waive the other thing to forfeit
the other thing. You haven't been given it yet. Whereas רב פפי
Rav Pappi feels even though it has conceptually a gift, okay, you
do have an existing claim and that claim can be waived even
in advance. The רשב"ם Rashbam does point out by the way the
earlier גמרא Gemara that spoke about protesting and so on and you
can't work my portion seems to work with the assumption that you
do have an existing claim right away. Okay, okay.
והא דרב פפא ורב פפי לא בפירוש איתמר, veha deRav Papa veRav
Pappi la beferush itmar, first wide line. Their positions were not said
explicitly, אלא מכללא איתמר. ela michlala itmar.
It was inferred from a different ruling they gave. Let's take a
look. Okay,
דההוא בכור דאזל זבין נכסי דידיה ודפשוט. dehu bechor de'azal zavin nichsei
didei udepashut. There was a certain בכור bechor that went and he
sold his portion and that of his of the other brother. אזלו
יתמי בני פשוט למיכל תמרי מהנה לקוחות. azlu yatmei benei pashut lemeichal
tamrei mehanei lekuchos. So then the children of the פשוט, pashut, let's
give them names ראובן Reuven and שמעון. Shimon. ראובן Reuven and יעקב
Yaakov died, left this field to ראובן Reuven and שמעון Shimon and
ראובן Reuven went and he sold the field to somebody else the
field that he had two thirds of a portion and שמעון Shimon
had one third. And that field had, you know, date trees in
it, palm trees. And then came along שמעון's Shimon kids and they
went into the field and maybe they weren't aware of what had
happened, that it had been sold, they were used to actually going
into that field when their father grandfather was alive and they continued
to eat the dates from that palm tree. Okay. So אזלו יתמי
בני פשוט למיכל תמרי מהנה לקוחות. azlu yatmei benei pashut lemeichal tamrei
mehanei lekuchos. They went to eat the dates from the field that
now belonged to the purchasers.
מחנהו. machinhu. So the purchasers beat them up, they kicked them out,
they said it's our field now. אמרו להו קרובים. amru lehu krovim.
So the relative said, לא מסתייא דזבנתינהו לנכסייהו אלא מימחא
נמי מחיתו להו. la mistaya dezavantinhu lenichsaihu ela mimcha nami machitu lehu.
They said to the, you know the relative said to the purchasers,
it's not sufficient that you bought our property, meaning again against our
will is presumably what the kids of שמעון Shimon are saying, you
know, like ראובן Reuven sold it, we had no say in this.
It's not sufficient that you now had a came and
and you've taken you know but now you're also beating them up?
אלא מימחא נמי מחיתו להו? ela mimcha nami machitu lehu? So אתו
לקמיה דרבא. asu lekamei deRava. So they came to רבא Rava to
discuss, you know, to debate this. Who has rights to this field?
אמר להו לא עשה ולא כלום. amar lehu lo asa velo klum.
He said, you know, to the purchasers,
to the purchasers or, you know, or to the or to שמעון's
Shimon children or whoever was there, he said to the to the
litigants, he said, you know what, the sale was not good. Yeah,
ראובן Reuven had no right to sell שמעון's Shimon portion. Okay, that's
all obvious that ראובן Reuven had no right to sell שמעון's Shimon
portion. Now, let's take a look here at the top of קכ"ו
עמוד ב. kuf chaf vav amud bet. מר סבר לא עשה כלום
בפלגא. mar savar lo asa klum bepalga. Now one of them, now
now there was apparently a debate, we don't even have it directly
cited between רב פפי Rav Pappi and רב פפא. Rav Papa. רב
פפי Rav Pappi felt, okay, he didn't do any good in half
of it, meaning in, you know, in שמעון's Shimon portion,
but also in, you know, his own portion. Excuse me, so I'm
going to read this like תוספות, Tosafot, okay? It was just a
simpler read. So מר סבר *Mar Savar* רב פפי *Rav Pappi* held
לא עשה כלום בפלגא *lo asa klum bephalga*. He didn't do anything
with half, meaning the half of the field that had a right
that שמעון *Shimon* had a right to, he was not good. But
his half, both his פשוט pashut *pashut* part portion and his בכור
bkhor, *bechor* portion, those two thirds, okay, that
actually wasn't a half, his portion, two thirds, the sale was good.
It just wasn't good for שמעון *Shimon*'s one third. Okay, ומר סבר
בכולהו *u'mar savar bekulhu*. Now it wasn't good for any part of
it. Now any part doesn't really mean any part, again this is
confusing, but anyway but at least reading it like תוספות *Tosafot* it
means it wasn't good for the third that belongs to שמעון *Shimon*
and it wasn't good for his בכור bkhor *bechor* portion. But for
his, you know, פשוט *pashut* portion, his simple portion, he was entitled
to sell. So that's at least the way תוספות *Tosafot* reads it,
that the first position is it did work it worked for both
his פשוט *pashut* portion and his בכור bkhor *bechor* portion. And in
the other one it only worked for his פשוט *pashut* portion. Okay,
so that's the way תוספות *Tosafot* says it, that doesn't fit the
word לא עשה *lo asa*, you know, where was
it? Hold on, ומר
סבר בכולהו *u'mar savar bekulhu*,
that it didn't work for any, because it did work for some.
It worked for his פשוט *pashut* portion. So the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam*
reads it rather, so again that's one read, that the question is
that according to the first position it works for you know, it
works for his two thirds, and according to the other position it
only works for his third, for his חלק פשוט *chelek pashut*, which
doesn't fit the language well of you know, of that he didn't
do anything. The רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* reads it differently but it becomes
even more complicated. That according to the first position it works for
his חלק בכורה *chelek bechora* but not his חלק פשוט *chelek pashut*,
and according to the second position it doesn't work for anything. Anyway
it's quite complicated, but bottom line is that the question here is
whether the בכור bkhor *bechor* was able to sell his בכור bkhor
*bechor* portion before חלוקה *chaluka*. And that's the question about whether the
בכור bkhor *bechor* has קודם חלוקה *kodem chaluka* or not. What it
doesn't get to is why I should assume that waiving my rights
for when we're dealing with the field means I'm waiving my rights
for everything. Because remember, in order to say that waiving my rights
for the field is a waiving my rights for everything requires two
assumptions. Assumption number one is that I intend to waive my rights
for everything. And assumption number two is that it is binding because
as a בכור bkhor, *bechor* I already have a claim even קודם
חלוקה *kodem chaluka* to my חלק בכור bkhor *chelek bechor*. All right.
So this debate of רב פפי *Rav Pappi* and רב פפא *Rav
Pappa* with ראובן *Reuven* selling his portion and שמעון *Shimon*'s portion, whether
it worked or not for ראובן *Reuven*'s own portion is
gets to the heart of whether ראובן *Reuven* has a right in
his חלק בכורה *chelek bechora* before it's been divided. But it doesn't
tell you whether waiving in one thing should be interpreted as waiving
in another thing. Anyway that's the debate. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara
*Gemara* says like this, שלח מתם *Shlach mitam*, בכור bechor, שמכר קודם
חלוקה לא עשה כלום *bechor shemachar kodem chaluka lo asa klum*. If
a בכור bechor *bechor* sold his בכור bechor, *bechor* portion before division
it's meaningless. אלמא אין לו לבכור קודם חלוקה *alma ein lo labechor
kodem chaluka*, and that is the side of רב *Rav* you know
of
who was it, of רב פפי *Rav Pappi* that a בכור bechor
*bechor* has no portion before the division. והלכתא יש לבכור קודם חלוקה
*vehilchesa yesh labechor kodem chaluka*, but the הלכה halacha *halacha* is no,
a בכור bechor *bechor* has a right a claim to his portion
before division so that his waiving will be meaningful and presumably also
his selling of it will be meaningful. And the debate of תוספות
*Tosafot* and the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* is do you assume the same
is true for his simple חלק *chelek*? You know, would we say
if he has a right to his בכור bechor. *bechor* portion which
is a מתנה matanah, *matana*, he certainly has a right to his
חלק *chelek* portion before it's been divided? That's what תוספות *Tosafot* assumes.
And the רשב"ם Rashbam *Rashbam* assumes no, only to his בכור bechor
*bechor* portion not his פשוט *pashut* portion, which is a little bizarre.
Okay, מר זוטרא מדרישבא פלג בצינא דפלפלי בהדי אחין בשוה *Mar Zutra
mideRishba pallag betzina depilpeli bahadi achin beshave*. So this מר זוטרא *Mar
Zutra* from רישבא *Rishba* divided with a basket of peppers with his
brothers equally even though he was a בכור bechor *bechor*. So there
it was, it was a certain genre, he was dividing it and
he was waiving implicitly his חלק בכורה *chelek bechora*. אתא לקמיה דרב
אשי אמר ליה amar lei, הואיל וויתרת במקצת ויתרת בכל הנכסים כולן
*ata lekamei deRav Ashi amar lei hovil uvitarta bemiktzat vitarta bechol hanichasim
kulan*. Since in one little thing you waived your rights, you waived
your rights for everything. Okay, so that as we've seen is the
consequence of the idea that a בכור bechor, *bechor* has קודם חלוקה
*kodem chaluka* that a בכור bechor *bechor* has a right before חלוקה
*chaluka* that he therefore can waive. Of course what still is like
I said very bizarre is it's one thing if he explicitly says
he's waiving his rights or if he wants to sell his rights,
those are things that make sense. But because you agree to an
equal division by a basket of peppers we're going to translate that
as a waiving. of your rights, you know, in everything, you know,
in the lands, in the multi-million dollar estate, that seems completely, completely
bizarre that we should make that jump. That's not a question of
whether you have rights, it's whether we interpret a tiny little thing
here as being a waiving of all of your rights. So I
really have no other way of understanding this other than that חז"ל
Chazal, maybe were somewhat discomforted by the idea of the פי שנים,
pishnayim, and therefore, you know, we see this a lot that the
Torah sets up לא יוכל לבכר lo yukhal levaker and all of
that, it's got to be double portion, it's got to be in
the right way. And then חז"ל, Chazal as we're about to also
see in the next משנה, mishnah, you know, in the whole position
of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא, Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka, you know, in
שכיב מרע, shkhiv mera, allow for a lot of reassigning of the
division of the estate. So the way here that they make this
idea a מתנה, the בכור, bechor and something that can be waived,
and then they go further to say and it can be waived
even before you receive it, and we're going to take a look
at the tiniest little single incident of waiving your rights in one
thing to be a waiving of your rights in everything, you know,
to me it only makes sense if חז"ל were a little
bit discomforted by this and that's part of a whole larger picture
of seeing more not as strict of a division as the Torah
allocates. Okay, but that's the discussion of יש לו לבכור קודם חלוקה
yesh lo l’bkhor kodem khalukah and a reading of small waiving into
a larger waiving.
Okay, so now we take a look at the next משנה. mishnah.
האומר איש פלוני בני בכור לא ייטול פי שנים, haomer ish ploni
bni bkhor lo yitol pishnayim, if somebody says this person is my
firstborn son, but he's not, I don't want to give him the
double portion. Direct violation of what the Torah says, you can't transfer
away the double portion. איש פלוני בני לא יירש עם אחיו, ish
ploni bni lo yirash im ekhav, or this is my son but
I don't want him to get a portion of what that he's
deserved, לא אמר כלום, lo amar klum, you can't explicitly try to
countermand the Torah's division of the estate. There are ways you can
do it around sort of roundabout ways, but you can't directly say
it's not going to work as the Torah says, שהתנה על מה
שכתוב בתורה, shehistna al ma shekatuv batorah, that you're stipulating against what
the Torah says. המחלק נכסיו על פיו, hamkhalek nekhassav al piv, now
if somebody is dividing up his estate based on his verbal instructions,
ריבה לאחד ומיעט לאחד, riba l’ekhad u’mi’et l’ekhad, והשוה להן את הבכור,
v’hishvah lahen et habkhor, and he says Reuven whatever this guy's going
to get sixty percent, that guy will get twenty percent, the בכור
bechor. will get or he'll just say the בכור bechor will get
the normal thing that everybody else will get. So in that case,
דבריו קיימים, divrav kayamim, it works if you do it as a
gift. Okay, so if it and this is going to be the
whole idea of מתנת שכיב מרע matnat shkhiv mera about the deathbed
bequest and the way effectively rabbinic wills and this is what we're
going to see more about, that the way you can work around
the Torah structure is not directly saying it won't work but to
turn everything into a gift. Now if you want the בכור bechor.
to not get double, you have to turn the entire estate into
a gift, because as long as there's something left of the estate
the בכור bechor will get a double portion of what is left
in the estate. So you can't leave anything that's not gifted if
you want the בכור bechor to totally be equal, you have to
divide all of your assets and divide them equally. Anyway, that's the
way to get around it to give it as a gift. Now
ואם אמר משום ירושה לא אמר כלום, v’im amar mishum yerushah lo
amar klum, but if you want to say that's the way it's
going to work as a type of an inheritance that won't, you
can't countermand the Torah structure of inheritance as we've seen, you can
be מוחל mokhel on the בכור, bechor the בכור bechor can be
מוחל, mokhel, you as a person who's about to die and bequeath
cannot countermand it but you can get around it by giving things
as a gift. כתב בין בתחילה בין באמצע בין בסוף משום מתנה
דבריו קיימים, katav bein bitkhilah bein b'emtza bein b'sof mishum matanah divrav
kayamim, however, even if you gave instructions or it was written out,
as long as there was a language of gift in the middle,
even if it was couched within a larger statement of ירושה, yerushah,
it will work. And we'll see about this more in the גמרא
Gemara. tomorrow. If you said, this person should be יורש, yoresh, twenty
percent of the estate and have it as a gift and be
יורש yoresh it, as long as somewhere in there you said and
have it as a gift, it should be given to him as
a gift and he should be יורש yoresh it, then that worked.
So you can frame it as a ירושה, yerushah, you can use
a lot of language of ירושה yerushah as long as you squeeze
in that language of gift there, we're going to make it operate
as a gift even though we all do understand that what you're
trying to do here is to reassign the ירושה. yerushah. Okay, let's
take a look at the גמרא. Gemara Obviously there'll be halachic differences
between if it's a gift and a ירושה. yerushah. לימא מתניתין דלא
כרבי יהודה, leima masnitin d’lo k’rabbi yehuda, let's say our משנה mishnah
that says you can't stipulate against ירושה yerushah is not like רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. דאי רבי יהודה, d’ei Rabbi Yehuda, because if it's
רבי יהודה, Rabbi Yehuda, האמר, ha’amar, he says, בדבר שבממון תנאו קיים,
bidvar shebamamon tna’o kayam, if it's a monetary matter you can actually
stipulate against the Torah's defining of parameters that are two-sided and that
are monetary issues. What does that mean? דתניא, d’tanya, we taught in
a ברייתא, braita, האומר לאשה הרי את מקודשת לי על מנת שאין
לי עליך שאר כסות ועונה, haomer l’ishah harei at mekudeshet li al
mnat she-ein li alayikh sheer k’sut v’onah, I'm you're מקודשת mekudeshet to
me on the condition that I don't have for you food, clothing,
and marital relations. you're married to me, you're מקודשת mekudeshet to me,
on the condition that I won't have the obligations the Torah puts
on me: clothing, food, and regular sex on regular intervals. שאר כסות
ועונה, She'er k'sut ve'onah,
food, clothing, and then sex. הרי זו מקודשת, Harei zu mekudeshet, so
the קידושין kiddushin takes effect ותנאו בטל. utna'o batel. דברי רבי מאיר.
Divrei Rabbi Meir. And your stipulation is meaningless because you tried to
stipulate against it, but the Torah says that's a consequence of being
married, you have those obligations. There is no way you can stipulate
against it. It's a package deal. רבי יהודה אומר בדבר שבממון תנאו
קיים. Rabbi Yehuda omer bidvar she-bemamon tna'o kayam. רבי יהודה Rabbi Yehuda
says, no, the monetary aspects, the payments for food and for clothing,
you can stipulate against it. The personal aspects, sex, conjugal duties, that
you can't stipulate against. That is part of the fundamental obligation of
marriage. So רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's general position is that when the
Torah puts financial obligations, economic,
monetary responsibility on parties, on two-sided what do you call it, deals,
then those are just the default obligations. But because it's an issue
of money and you can always give money back and you can
always be מוחל mochel debts and so on, people have the freedom
to stipulate differently or stipulate against it. So for example, if a
שומר חנם shomer chinam has certain obligations for negligence but not for
גניבה ואבידה, gneiva va'aveida, you can say, well, those are the default
obligations of a שומר חנם. shomer chinam. But we can stipulate if
you're willing to watch my object or you're a שומר שכר, shomer
sachar, whatever it is, we can stipulate a different set of obligations.
Okay, anything that's about monetary obligations since you can enter into it
by two parties contractually and since any obligations can always be waived,
so even when the Torah assigns them, they can always be stipulated
against or framed differently. That's רבי יהודה'ס Rabbi Yehuda's position. As long
as it's monetary, makes a lot of sense. Okay. But the גמרא
Gemara says, so this seems that this would not be רבי יהודה.
Rabbi Yehuda. So the גמרא Gemara gives the obvious answer which I've
been hinting towards all along. So the גמרא Gemara, says, no, אפילו
תימא רבי יהודה, afilu teima Rabbi Yehuda, it can even be רבי
יהודה. Rabbi Yehuda. התם ידע וקמחלה. Hatam yada ve-kamachla. In the case
by קידושין kiddushin or in the case of שומר, shomer, all those
cases, the person can be waiving what's coming to them. Or the
way I would sort of say it is, they're two-sided transactions and
therefore because both sides are agreeing, we can agree to different parameters.
הכא לא קמחלה. Hacha lo kamachla. Here the heir is not being
מוחל. mochel. And the way I would say it, the רשב"ם says,
well, what if he is מוחל? mochel? He says I מוחל mochel
my portion? And they're like well, you're just doing it to make
your father happy. You don't really mean it. We can't really trust
it. So I would say מוחל mochel is a little bit deeper.
It doesn't just mean the absence of מוחל. mochel. It means that
an inheritance happens automatically. It is not a transaction that is entered
to by both sides who are agreeing on the parameters. And since
it happens automatically, you don't have active parties that are in a
position
to restructure it. Should also say even the guy who's dying, it's
not that he does an act of bequeathing. He just dies and
then the Torah transfers the property. So it's fundamentally different than a
two-sided transaction. אמר רב יוסף, Amar Rav Yosef, said רב יוסף, Rav
Yosef, אמר איש פלוני בני בכורי הוא נוטל פי שנים. amar ish
ploni beni bechori hu notel pi shenayim.
If somebody says this person is my firstborn son, then he gets
double portion like the משנה'ס Mishna's been teaching. If he says איש
פלוני בכור הוא, ish ploni bechor hu, this person is a בכור,
bechor and people understood that it was his son, אינו נוטל פי
שנים, eino notel pi shenayim, that's not enough for him to get
double. Why not? דלמא בכור דאמא קאמר. dilma bechor de-ima ka'amar. Maybe
he meant he's firstborn to his mother. Maybe. But the בכור bechor
of the Torah that gets a double portion is not the first
male child of the mother, it is the first male child of
the father. Now people say well, okay, but this is the only
woman we know you're married to. How do you know? Maybe he
had a firstborn son with another woman halfway across the world. What
do you know about what he did before he married this woman?
Okay, so again, even though by the context we would think it
means firstborn, we're not prepared to read it that way.
ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרבה בר בר חנה, Hahu de-ata lekamei de-Rabba bar
bar Chana, a person came to רבה בר בר חנה, Rabba bar
bar Chana, אמר ליה, מוחזקני בזה שהוא בכור. muchzakani be-ze she-hu bechor.
So I, the guy died and somebody said and the רשב"ם said
there was another witness with him because you need two witnesses. We,
this person was already established, well known to be the firstborn son
of this guy who died and therefore he should get a double
portion. אמר ליה מנא ידעת? Amar lei mana yadata? How do you
know it? So he said back, דהוה קרי ליה אבוה בוכרא סכלא.
da-hava kari lei avuh buchra sichla. His father used to call him
"you idiot firstborn son." You know, you're firstborn, you're supposed to be
smart, you're supposed to be, the leader of your brothers. You know,
what a foolish firstborn son you were. So okay, but he's a
firstborn son. Okay? So the גמרא, so רבא Rava said, no, sorry,
he's not entitled to a double portion. דילמא בוכרא דאימא הוא, Dilma
bukhra de-imma hu, maybe he's just firstborn from his mother but not
the father's firstborn. דכל בוכרא דאימא נמי בוכרא סכלא קרו ליה, De-chol
bukhra de-imma nami bukhra sikhla karu lei, maybe you know, any firstborn
of a mother who's not the firstborn of a father is called
a foolish firstborn. It doesn't mean the person himself is foolish, it
means it's like he's, you know, he's like a pseudo-firstborn, not a
real firstborn because you're a firstborn on your mother's and that's good
for פטר רחם petter rechem but not a firstborn on the father's,
which is more significant in terms of the patriarchy and in terms
of the double portion. So the סכלא sikhla means you're a missed
firstborn or something of that nature. Okay. ההוא דאתא Hahu de-ata first
wide line. ההוא דאתא לקמיה דרב חנינא Hahu de-ata lekamei de-Rav Chanina
five lines from the bottom or eight lines from the bottom. ההוא
דאתא לקמיה דרב חנינא. Hahu de-ata lekamei de-Rav Chanina. Somebody came to
רב חנינא Rav Chanina similar case, said, מוחזקני בזה שהוא בכור. Muchzakni
be-zeh she-hu bechor. Somebody came to רב חנינא Rav Chanina similar case,
said, I know this guy and again the רשב"ם says it was
another person, it was two witnesses, I know this guy's a בכור,
he should get פי שנים. pi shenayim. אמר ליה מנא ידעת? Amar
lei mana yadata? How do you know? אמר ליה דכי הוו אתו
לגבי אבוה Amar lei de-ki havu atu gabbei avuha
when, you know, people would come to his father, אמר להו amar
lehu he would say to them, because his father apparently was a
doctor or something like that, okay,
זילו לגבי שכחת ברי, Zilu legabbei Shichchas beri, go to שכחת Shichchas
my son, that was the boy's name,
דבכור הוא, de-bechor hu, he's a firstborn son, ומסי רוקיה, u-masi rokeih,
and his spit, you know, has healing
properties. The way the רשב"ם said it is that people would have
eye ailments and they would believe there was a belief that the
spit of a firstborn son, you spit in your eye, would actually
be helpful. All right. So then the response back was, okay, ודילמא
בכור דאמא הוא? ve-dilma bechor de-imma hu? I don't buy it because
maybe it was his, you know, still firstborn of the mother. And
then the... no, but here that's not a good pushback. גמירי בכור
דאבא מסי רוקיה בכור דאמא לא מסי רוקיה. Gemiri bechor de-abba masi
rokeih bechor de-imma lo masi rokeih. No, the spit of a firstborn
only on the father, only if the father's firstborn has these medicinal
properties. Now whether or not we believe of these medicinal properties, the
bottom line was, was that the fact that the father was saying
it clearly demonstrates that the father
understood, even if this belief was totally, you know, crazy and wrong,
but nevertheless, it clearly shows that the father saw him as the
firstborn on the father, as a firstborn father's son because otherwise he
would not have recommended this medical treatment.
Okay.
אמר רבי אמי, Amar Rabbi Ami, טומטום שנקרע ונמצא זכר אינו נוטל
פי שנים. Tumtum she-nikra ve-nimtza zachar eino notel pi shenayim.
So if somebody is born as a טומטום, tumtum, which is somebody
whose genitalia is covered up, definitely a male or a female, we
just don't know because his genitalia is covered up. And here what
we're going to... so normally the way הלכה treats that person is
a ספק, safek, but he's definitely one or the other, we're just
ignorant and it's just a question of our ignorance and we have
to deal הלכתית halachically with our ignorance. Here, however, we're introducing the
idea that if that is how somebody is born, then even if
it becomes clear afterwards, the skin covering tears and we see what
his genitalia are and we see that he's a boy, the fact
that it was covered up when he was born does
somewhat compromise his הלכתי halachic status in some areas, you know, especially
areas in which at the moment of birth it determines status,
you know, in certain ways in terms of being seen as a
male or as a firstborn. Let's take a look. Okay. So he
says, טומטום שנקרע ונמצא זכר, Tumtum she-nikra ve-nimtza zachar, after he was
born it was torn and it was discovered he was a male,
אינו נוטל פי שנים, eino notel pi shenayim, he does not get
double, he's not seen as the בכור since at the moment of
birth he was not recognized as the בכור because had he... he
might have been a girl, and as a girl he would not
have had the status of a בכור. דאמר קרא והיה הבן הבכור
לשניאה, De-amar kra ve-haya ha-ben ha-bechor laseni'ah, the firstborn son shall
be for the hated wife, עד שיכא בן משעת הויה. ad she-yehei
ben mi-sha'at havaya. והיה הבן, Ve-haya ha-ben, so he is a son
from the moment of הויה, havaya, he's recognized, not just objectively God
knows, he's recognized as being a male from the moment of birth.
And that is significant in order for him to be entitled to
his בכור status. רב נחמן בר יצחק אמר אף אינו נידון כבן
סורר ומורה. Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak amar af eino nidon ke-ben sorer
u-moreh. He's also not treated as a בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer
u-moreh. דאמר קרא כי יהיה לאיש בן סורר ומורה, De-amar kra ki
yihyeh le-ish ben sorer u-moreh, when a person has a son who
is wayward and rebellious, עד שיהא בן משעת הויה. ad she-yehei ben
mi-sha'at havaya. Now even though there the status of סורר ומורה sorer
u-moreh only comes later in life, but because he was not a
בן, ben, he was not seen as a son when he was
born, he does not fit into this בן סורר ומורה ben sorer
u-moreh category. אמימר אמר אף אינו ממעט חלק בכורה. Amemar amar af
eino mema'et chelek bechorah. אמימר Amemar says top of כ"ז עמוד א',
Chaf-zayin amud aleph, he would... if somebody was a second-born son, it
would not impact the size of the portion that the בכור would
get. All right, I'll do the math in a minute. שנאמר וילדו
לו בנים, Shene'emar ve-yaldu lo banim, that, you know... you know, and
that speaks this man has two wives, whatever, and they give birth
to him to sons, and one is the first-born and the other's
not. עד שיהא בן בשעת לידה. ad she-yehei ben be-sha'at leidah. All
of, in order for any of the sons to be relevant for
how we think about בכור, they have to be בן ben at
the moment of birth. All right, so what does that mean? It
means that if let's say you had three sons. All right, and
if they were all born and known to be male at the
time, then and you had property worth $400. So the בכור would
get everybody would get a hundred as a פשוט and the בכור
would get another hundred as the בכור. So his size of the
בכור portion would be a hundred.
Now, however, one of the sons was born as a טומטום tumtum
and only later was it torn and it was discovered he was
a בכור. So if you had only only
two sons, not three, and an estate worth 400, well as then
you would divide it into three portions and the בכור's portion and
and the בכור would get 266 and the other guy would get
133. So in that scenario, the בכור's portion would be 133. So
when you're deciding the size of a בכור portion, don't look at
the guy who is born you know count amongst the sons the
one who was born as a טומטום. tumtum. So now with only
two sons, the בכור's portion is 133, so that is the protected
size of the בכור's portion 133. Now you're left with
266 and now you have three sons and now you divide the
266 equally among three. All right, so and let's just read one
more. רב שיזבי אמר אף אנן נמי לשמונה. Rav Shizbi amar af
anan nami le-shmonah. He does not have a ברית מילה brit milah
on day eight, it doesn't override שבת. shabbat. דאמר קרא אשה כי
תזריע וילדה זכר וביום השמיני ימול. de-amar kra ishah ki tazria ve-yaldah
zachar u-vayom ha-shmini yimol. When she gives forth seed and it's a
male, and then you have the obligation to do the ברית מילה
brit milah on day eight. עד שיהא זכר משעת לידה. ad she-yehei
zachar mi-sha'at leidah. Okay, until he is a male only from the
time of birth. Now again, a lot of this makes sense, makes
sense. I mean, we wouldn't have said it, but if we're going
to say it, I mean we're not going to say that a
normal טומטום tumtum שנקרע she-nikra does not have a full status of
male, but all of these have to do with things that are
immediate status is defined at the moment of birth, however with the
exception of the בן סורר ומורה. ben sorer u-moreh. So it is
a little bit, raises interesting questions, you know, about how this is
challenging this person's status for future aspects in life and what is
the scope of this because normally again, we normally just treat this
person as a ספק safek and then that ספק safek is clarified
and here we are seeing that for some הלכות halachot it was
important to know at the time of birth.